NOLWAZI **HLOPHE**

8 Onyx, 34 Lemonwood Street, Eco-Park Estate, Centurion, 0157 · +27 (0) 78 144 0531 nolwazihlophe@gmail.com · LinkedIn Profile · https://nolwazihlophe.github.io

I am an experienced financial regulation and supervision specialist with a demonstrated history of working in financial regulation and supervision, capacity building and research.

EXPERIENCE

DECEMBER 2020 - PRESENT

DEPUTY DIRECTOR FINANCIAL REGULATION AND SUPERVISION, DIGITAL FRONTIERS INSTITUTE

- 1. **Program management** for the Digital Financial Inclusion Supervision (<u>DFIS</u>) Program with Toronto Centre and CGAP
- 2. Contributing to the ongoing Instant and Inclusive Payment Systems (IIPS) program: Regulating and Governing IIP Systems <u>course</u>
- 3. **Regulatory lead** for the Certified Digital Financial Practitioner (<u>CDFP</u>) courses: Anti-Money Laundering Compliance, Regulation of Digital Financial Services, Digital Identity and Certificate In Digital Money (CIDM)—Financial regulation and National Payment Systems course content

APRIL 2020 – DECEMBER 2020

REGULATORY PROGRAM LEAD, DIGITAL FRONTIERS INSTITUTE

Regulatory lead for e-learning courses: Regulation of Digital Financial Services, Digital Identity, Anti-money Laundering Compliance, Inclusive and Instant Payments: Governance and Regulation Stream.

Course development: Quiz/test development, assignment development and Course review and update

Co-convener of Digital Identity Week 2020.

Presentations:

- 1. **Cryptocurrency and Blockchain Course Closure (2020)**: FSD Mozambique DFS issues faced by financial regulators
- 2. Ethiopia 4th CIDM Alumni Zoom Meeting (2020): current DFS issues faced by regulators
- 3. Digital Identity Week (2020): eSwatini case study

JANUARY 2019 - MARCH 2020

SENIOR RESEARCH ANALYST, CENTER FOR FINANCIAL REGULATION AND INCLUSION (CENFRI)

Project management: Zambia Payments Diagnostic and Regulating for Innovation in Payments: Reserve Bank of Malawi

Research and drafting: AFI Toolkit: Aligning financial integrity and financial inclusion, Eswatini central bank digital currency (CBDC) diagnostic: Motivations for CBDC in Eswatini, Zambia Payments Diagnostic, An analysis of ID proxy initiatives across the globe

Presentations:

- Consultative meeting on central bank-issued digital currencies (2019): CBDCs, Benefits
 Potential Risks
- 2. **Africa Global Payment Summit (2019)**: Supply-side barriers to remittances in Sub-Saharan Africa

Stakeholder engagement, client contracting and drafting proposals

MAY 2018 - DECEMBER 2018

PROJECT MANAGER: CBE INTELLIGENCE HUB, CENTRAL BANK OF ESWATINI

Managing Activities of the Fintech Unit: Fintech Challenge Eswatini (FinTech Challenge

Bootcamp), CBE Regulatory Sandbox Framework, Idea Factory

Strategy Development for the CBE Fintech Unit: 3-year strategy and plan of activities for Fintech Unit

Conference Presentation (2018): Launch of the Fintech Challenge

NOVEMBER 2017 - DECEMBER 2018

MACROPRUDENTIAL ANALYST, CENTRAL BANK OF ESWATINI

NOVEMBER 2015 - OCTOBER 2017

GRADUATE TRAINEE, CENTRAL BANK OF ESWATINI

Financial sector data collection and analysis

Conduct Macroprudential Analysis: Investment Managers/Advisors, Savings And Credit Cooperatives (SACCOs), Household Debt

Drafting: Compiling The Guidance Note On Effective Stakeholder Co-Ordination Mechanisms For National Financial Inclusion Strategy Implementation, Drafting The Macroprudential Framework – Systemic Risk Analysis For The SADC Region

National Risk Assessment Of Swaziland: Financial Inclusion Module Compiling The Financial Inclusion Index For Swaziland (World Bank Tool)

Planning: Global Money Week Activities, annual Financial Stability Conference

Conference Presentation (2018): Swaziland Economic Conference

JUNE 2017

ECONOMETRICS TUTOR, UNIVERSITY OF CAPE TOWN: AFRICAN INSTITUTE OF FINANCIAL MARKETS AND RISK MANAGEMENT (AIFMRM)

Class tests and exam development and facilitating tutorials

Lecturing on risk management analysis and time series models: market risk analysis, time series models

Coursera course content development: Financial regulation in Emerging Markets and the rise of fintech companies

JANUARY 2013 - OCTOBER 2015

ASSISTANT LECTURER, UNIVERSITY OF PRETORIA

Lecturing first year and senior students (Hatfield campus) in **Academic Information Management** (AIM 101, AIM 111 and AIM 121) and in software applications, by preparing specific outcomes integrating the use of a computer and internet technologies; as well as attending to ad hoc admin duties.

EDUCATION

OCTOBER 2020

DIGITAL IDENTITY, DIGITAL FRONTIERS INSTITUTE

MAY 2020

ANTI-MONEY LAUNDERING COMPLIANCE, DIGITAL FRONTIERS INSTITUTE

DECEMBER 2018

PROJECT MANAGEMENT FOR NON-PROJECT MANAGERS PROGRAMME, GIBS BUSINESS SCHOOL

JUNE 2016

MCOM (COURSEWORK) ECONOMICS, UNIVERSITY OF PRETORIA

Dissertation title: Environmental Kuznets Curve: Factors Affecting it in South Africa

Supervisor: Prof. Roula Inglesi-Lotz

DECEMBER 2013

BCOM (HONS) ECONOMICS, UNIVERSITY OF PRETORIA

Dissertation title: Economic Impacts of Legalizing Rhino Horn Trade

Supervisor: Prof. Jan van Heerden

DECEMBER 2012

BCOM ECONOMETRICS, UNIVERSITY OF PRETORIA

OTHER ACHIEVEMENTS

- Bursaries/scholarships:
 - NRF Grant Holder-Linked Bursary towards my MCom (Coursework) Economics (2015)
 - Achievement Bursary from the University of Pretoria (2008)
- Presentations, podcasts and webinars:
 - Digital Frontiers Institute: CBDC in Africa
 - Digital Frontiers Institute: Financial Regulation and Supervision: are they the same or different?
 - Blockchain and Digital Currency: The Future of Money (GetSmarter): <u>Guest Lecturer CBDC</u> and financial inclusion
 - World Digital Economic Council & FinTech4Good: The CBDC Forum III <u>CBDC Development in</u> Africa: Country Case Studies Panel
- Publications:
 - Title: <u>Does Financial Development Mean Financial Inclusion? A Causal Analysis for Eswatini</u>
 Journal: African Review of Economics and Finance | Volume: 10 (2) Date: Dec 2018, Pages: 120 133
 - Title: Regtech and The Central Bank | Publisher: Central Bank of Eswatini CentraTalk Magazine | Issue: 1 | Date: Jan 2019
 - **Title**: Regulatory Influence: The Imperative for Sustainability Through Innovation in Emerging Markets | **Publisher**: RegTech Africa | **Date**: April 2021
 - Title: <u>Is Capacity Building a Necessary Requirement for Enhanced and Forward-Looking Regulatory Change?</u> | **Publisher**: *Digital Banker Africa* | **Date**: May 2021

REFERENCES

Barry Cooper barryc@cenfri.org

Philile Nxumalo phililen@centralbank.org.sz

David Porteous

david@digitalfrontiers.org

Xavier Martin

xavier@digitalfrontiers.org